A Finding Aid to the David Novros Papers, 1963-2008, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
David Novros papers
1963-2008
Archives of American Art
Novros, David, 1941-
AAA.novrdavi
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of abstract painter David Novros are dated 1963 to 2008, and measure 1.0 linear foot. Correspondence, records relating to the Liaunig Boat House commission (Middleburgh, NY), interview transcripts, printed material, and photographs document the painter's professional career.
Provenance
Gift of David Novros, 2009
Related Material
An oral history interview with David Novros was conducted by Michael Brennan for the Archives of American Art in 2008.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
David Novros (1941-) is an abstract painter in New York, NY.
Abstract painter David Novros was born in Los Angeles in 1941 and lived with his family in Van Nuys, California. His father, Lester Novros, was an artist whose interest in movement eventually led him to the Walt Disney Company, where he worked on animation projects. In 1941 he established his own production company, Graphic Films, and began teaching in the Cinema Department of the University of Southern California. Both David and his brother Paul were enamored with film; David turned to painting, but Paul followed in their father's line of work and became an award-winning film producer.
David entered the University of Southern California and studied painting with James Jervaisee. He made a few student films and sometimes worked with his father, but before long he turned to painting. During the summer of 1961, Novros attended courses at Yale and met Chuck Close, Brice Marden, and Vija Celmins.
After earning a B.F.A. in 1963, Novros completed his Army Reserve obligations and travelled in Europe. He moved to New York City in 1964 and met many Minimalist artists. Over the next several years, Novros's rectangular paintings gave way to multi-panel paintings and then to shaped panels. From the late 1960s through the 1970s, Novros developed a reputation as a geometric abstractionist. He showed at Park Place Gallery and had a solo exhibition at Virginia Dwan Gallery (Los Angeles) in 1966; the next year, his work was again presented at Park Place Gallery and at the Virginia Dwan Gallery (New York). Several solo exhibitions followed at Klaus Kertess's influential Bykert Gallery, as well as at other venues.
Novros participated in important exhibitions of abstraction, among them "Systemic Painting" (Guggenheim Museum, 1966), "Color and Structure" (Whitney Museum of American Art, 1971), and "Abstract-Geometry-Painting: Selected Geometric Abstract Painting in America since 1945" (Albright-Knox Gallery, 1989). In 1970, he was awarded a Guggenheim Foundation Fellowship.
In the 1970s, Novros turned to fresco painting, and his eventual decision to focus on murals effectively removed him from the commercial gallery scene. One of his earliest commissions was a fresco painted in 1970 for the second floor of Donald Judd's studio/home. Other commissions include: Solar Triptych, a radial triptych that opens and closes throughout the day, for the lobby of Union Station, Newark, NJ (1984); a fresco in the Old Court House, Miami (1984); a painted-glass and copper fresco in the Gross Building, Winslow, Arizona (1994-1996); and the Liaunig Boat House with fresco paintings, Middleburgh, NY (1996-2003). A number of museums in the United States and Europe include Novros's work in their permanent collections, among them: Menil Collection, Museum of Modern Art, Whitney Museum of American Art, Museum Liaunig (Austria), and Daimler contemporary (Berlin).
Mr. Novros lives and works in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of abstract painter David Novros are dated 1963 to 2008, and measure 1.0 linear foot. Correspondence, records relating to the Liaunig Boat House commission (Middleburgh, NY), interview transcripts, printed material, and photographs document the painter's professional career.
The vast majority of correspondence consists of incoming letters. The only reciprocal exchanges preserved are with art historian Charles Hope and the Menil Collection. Letters are from artists Rory McEwen, Paul Mogensen, and Ken Price; writers Frances Colpitt and Claudine Humblet; and from other colleagues and friends. The letters David Novros wrote to his family between 1963 and 1979 recount his travels and describe in some detail - many with accompanying illustrations and diagrams - work in progress, exhibitions, and commissions. Also preserved are copies of his letters to the Trustees of the Donald Judd Estate and Ranier Judd concerning the Marfa, Texas properties and projects, his Spring Street studio in New York City, and the Judd Foundation. Novros's letters to editors concern art-related articles that appeared in The New York Review of Books, The New York Times, Los Angeles Times, and other publications.
Peter Liaunig's commission for a boat house with three fresco paintings in Middleburgh, New York, is documented by correspondence, plans, and designs. The "Boat House Diary, Middleburgh, NY," kept by Novros August 10-15, 2003, describes the process of painting the frescoes with the assistance of Jason, and notes materials and techniques used.
Interview transcripts are of Phong Bui's conversation with David Novros, published June 2008 in The Brooklyn Rail, and an unpublished interview Novros conducted with sculptor Robert Graham in 2008.
Printed material about or mentioning David Novros consists of articles and reviews, exhibition announcements and posters. Items written by Novros are a review of Jackson Pollock and two poems.
Photographs are of David Novros with his family and friends. There are also views of the Novros family's home in Van Nuys, California, and Indian-painted rocks at Sears Point, Arizona that influenced Novros' art.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Correspondence, 1963-2008 (Boxes 1-2; 0.4 linear ft.)
Series 2: Liaunig Boat House, 1998-2004 (Box 2, OV3; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 3: Interview Transcripts, 2008 (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1966-2008 (Box 2, OV 4; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 5: Photographs, 1976-1999 (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Poems; Painting -- Technique; Transcripts; Interviews; Illustrated letters; Diaries; Humblet, Claudine, 1946-; Hope, Charles; Graham, Robert, 1938-; Colpitt, Frances; Pollock, Jackson, 1912-1956; McEwen, Rory, 1932-; Judd, Donald, 1928-; Price, Kenneth, 1935-2012; Bui, Phong, 1964-
- Correspondence, 1963-2008; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 1-2; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence with art historian Charles Hope regards a letter to the editor of The New York Review of Books written by Novros in response to Hope's exhibition review of "Venice and the North." Novros's correspondence with the Menil Collection and Menil Foundation concerns the acquisition and exhibition of his work, with notes and background information.
  The vast majority of correspondence consists of incoming letters. Found here are letters from artists Rory McEwen, Paul Mogensen, and Ken Price. Rory McEwen, who wrote over an extended period, sent a small, undated watercolor portrait of himself working in the kitchen with his wife. Enclosed with Frances Colpitt's letters are manuscripts of her review of Minimalism by James Meyer, a catalogue entry about David Novros for the Blanton Museum of Art's exhibition "Reimagining Space: the Park Place Gallery Group in 1960s New York," and a copy of a letter she sent to Donald Judd's daughter about his estate. Letters from Claudine Humblet concern her book, La Nouvelle Abstraction Américaine de 1950 à 1970, and include a copy of "David Novros: ou la quête d'un art classique."
  Letters that David Novros wrote to his family between 1963 and 1979 recount his travels and describe in some detail work in progress, exhibitions, and commissions; they often include diagrams and illustrations. His letters to the Trustees of the Donald Judd Estate and Ranier Judd are about Judd's Marfa, Texas properties and projects, his New York City studio on Spring Street, and the Judd Foundation. Novros's letters to editors concern art-related articles that appeared in The New York Review of Books, The New York Times, Los Angeles Times, and other publications.
  - Bober, Michael (cousin), 1976-2009, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colpitt, Frances, circa 1999-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cooper, Paula - Cuomo, Mario, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Cooper, Paula
    Cuomo, Mario
  - Editors, Letters to, 1988-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Goldmark, Steve, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hope, Charles, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Humblet, Claudine, 1999-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Irish Museum of Modern Art, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Judd, Donald (Estate of), 1997-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - McEwen, Rory, 1973-1982, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Meanders, Nabuko Yoshizawa, 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Menil Collection, 1987-2008, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mogensen, Paul, 2003-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Novros Family ( see also: Bober, Michael), Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Father to David, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Paul (brother) to David, 2007, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - David to Family, 1963-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - David to Family, 1971-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - David to Family, 1975-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - David to Family, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - David to Family, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Price, Ken - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1999-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Price, Ken
    Whitney Museum of American Art
  - Unidentified, 1992-2006, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Bonnie
    Dee[lun?]
    Josef
    Phil
- Liaunig Boat House, 1998-2004; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Box 2, OV3; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Among the designs for painted fresco walls are many small drawings in ink and color pencil. Description and narrative consists of a printed sheet with building specifications, and "Boat House Diary, Middleburgh, NY" kept by Novros. Diary entries dated Aug. 10-15, 2003 describe the process of painting the frescoes with the assistance of Jason, and note materials and techniques used.
  - Correspondence, 1998-2004, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Description and Narrative, 2002-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Designs for Painted Fresco Walls (original drawings), 2001, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Plans, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Original Drawings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Photocopies, 2001-2002, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Liaunig Boat House - Oversized Plans (original drawings), 2001, undated; Archival Resource Key; (oversized material from box 2, folder 4) (Box OV 3)
  - Photographs, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Interview Transcripts, 2008; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Phong Bui's interview with David Novros was published in The Brooklyn Rail, June 2008. The interview Novros conducted with scuptor Robert Graham is unpublished.
  - "David Novros in Conversation with Phong Bui [editor of The Brooklyn Rail" (third edit; final edit), 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Robert Graham in conversation with David Novros,", 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Printed Material, 1966-2008; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Box 2, OV 4; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Printed material about or mentioning David Novros consists of articles and reviews, exhibition announcements and posters. Items written by Novros are a review of a Jackson Pollock exhibition and two poems.
  - About/Mentioning David Novros, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Articles, 1966-2008, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1968-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Exhibition Posters, 1966-1979; Archival Resource Key; (oversized material housed in OV4) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - By David Novros (exhibition review; poems), 1967, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - About/Mentioning David Novros - Exhibition Posters, 1966-1979; Archival Resource Key; (oversized material from box 2, folder 13) (Box OV 4)
- Photographs, 1976-1999; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; (Box 2; 0.1 linear ft.)
  Photographs of Novros with family and include: brother Paul, Robert Graham, Rory and Romana (Ruby) McEwen, and unidentified individuals. Among the pictures of places are the Novros family's home in Van Nuys, California, and rocks at Sears Point, Arizona, painted with Indian images that influenced his art.
  - David Novros, 1976-1995, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - David Novros with Others, 1976-1999, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified Individual, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Arizona (Sears Point painted rocks), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - California (childhood home, Van Nuys; unidentified landscapes), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Nevada, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified Landscapes and Buildings, 1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)